アイツだよ
It’s him.
どうしよう
What now?
Why isn’t he attacking?
どうして攻撃してこないの？
それに…
Also…
Don’t change your tone.
声のトーンを変えるな
たぶん 俺たちに
みんなのところまで
He probably wants us to lead him to the others.
案内させるつもりなんだ
運河に出れば…
Can we escape into a canal?
No, we won’t make it.
いや 無理だ
The minute we go faster, he’ll attack us.
こちらが速度を上げた途端
攻撃してくるだろう
まさか もうダメってこと？
Are you saying we have no chance?
ちょっと待って 今 考える
Hold on.
Let me think about this.
こんなことになるなんて
思ってもみなかった
This is completely beyond my expectations.
今だって 今夜 起こったことが
信じられないの
I still can’t believe what happened tonight.
大勢の人が亡くなったわ
So many people are dead.
誰も助けられなかった
Nobody could save them.
That’s not all.
それだけじゃない
I abandoned Okano-san and that other woman.
私は岡野さんたちを見捨てて…
ううん 見殺しにしたのよ
No.
I left them to die.
どうして こんなことになったの？
How did it come to this?
一体 何が悪かったというの？
Where did we go wrong?
I don’t want to die like this.
こんなところで死にたくない
何も分からないままで
I don’t want to die clueless.
人生が終わりになるなんて
絶対に嫌よ
Please calm down.
落ち着いて 同じトーンで
Don’t change your tone.
教育委員会なんて大嫌いよ
I hate the Board of Education.
私たちを簡単に殺そうとした
They had no qualms about trying to kill us.
They sent tainted cats…
不浄猫を使って
だけど 今なら分かるわ
But now I understand.
Now I know they were just afraid.
あの人たちは
ただ おびえていたんだって
They were afraid something like this would happen.
今晩みたいな恐ろしい出来事が
起こるのを
They felt compelled to prevent it.
防がなきゃいけないって
ただ そう思ってたんだわ
Simple as that.
だからといって
私たちや真理亜にしたことを
That’s not to say I’ve forgiven them for what they did to us and Maria.
許す気には なれないけど…
真理亜が死んだなんて信じない
信じたくない
I can’t believe Maria is dead.
I don’t want to believe it.
それに私たちの大切な仲間だった
顔のない少年
And then there’s our other friend.
The boy without a face.
私は彼が好きだった
I loved him.
I don’t want to die without knowing his name.
彼の名前も思い出せないまま
死ぬのは嫌なの
I feel the same, Saki.
俺も同じ気持ちだよ 早季
記憶を奪われたせいで
I can’t get over my feelings for him because my memories were taken from me.
彼への気持ちに
ふんぎりがつかない
Satoru…
覚…
That’s why we can’t die here.
だから ここでは
死ねない
Episode
Twenty
A Cold and
Sunlit Place
なんとかして 気づかれないように
舟から降りられれば
We have to somehow make it out of the boat unseen.
How about this?
こんなのは どうかしら？
Say this is the boat behind us…
これが 後ろの舟として
よし 運河に入ったら
すぐに仕掛けるよ
Okay. Let’s try that as soon as we’ve entered the canal.
そっちが私たちの舟
That’s our boat there.
Make a mirror between the two boats.
２そうの間に鏡を作る
舟の形は違うけど
今の距離と暗がりで
Our boats aren’t the same,
but in the darkness and at our distance, I don’t think he can tell the difference.
見分けは つかないと思う
That won’t work.
ダメだ
風景が動く方向が逆になるよ
The river banks will seem to recede in the opposite direction.
At our speed, I don’t think he’ll notice.
今ぐらいのスピードなら
気がつかないんじゃない？
I guess you’re right.
なるほど
We can then float each other to the shore and erase the mirror afterwards.
鏡の陰で お互いを岸に運んだら
鏡を消す
やってみよう
Let’s try it.
終わったら なるべく遠くへ
舟を突き放した方がいいな
We should give our boat a good push after that.
準備は いい？
Are you ready?
Yeah.
大丈夫？
Are you okay?
Yeah.
やっぱり痛む？
Does it hurt?
裾が引っかかっただけだから
大丈夫
I just ripped the hem of my yukata. It’s okay.
やっぱり水路だけじゃなく
他の交通手段も
Don’t you think we need more means of
transportation than just the waterways, Saki-chan?
確保すべきだと思わない？
早季ちゃん
We could really use some electricity at the library, Saki.
図書館の方にも この電力を…
なんとかならないかしら 早季
伝声管以外の伝達手段ですか
Some other way to communicate than with speaking tubes?
渡辺早季さん どう思いますか？
What do you think, Watanabe Saki-san?
Come on, wash your hands, Saki.
ほら 手を洗ってきなさい 早季
Watanabe-san.
渡辺さん
早季？
Saki?
早季
早季ちゃん？
Saki.
Saki-chan?
早季…
Saki?
早季は私が守ってあげるから
I’ll protect you, Saki.
Let’s rest for a bit.
少し休んで
動きやすい服を借りていこう
I’ll go borrow some traveling clothes.
休める所があってよかった
Good thing we found a place to rest.
そうだね…
Yeah.
使えそう？
Think we can use it?
Yeah, but the wheels look damaged.
車輪が少し傷んでるけど
まだ戦闘が続いているんだ
The fighting hasn’t subsided.
余計な憶測をしても しかたない
No point in wondering what’s going on there.
早くみんなと合流しよう
Let’s hurry and find the others.
Yeah.
ねえ やっぱり 森を行った方が
よかったんじゃない？
Hey, shouldn’t we have gone through the forest?
これじゃ丸見えよ
We’re sitting ducks here.
No, we can’t afford to waste time.
ダメだ 手遅れになるかもしれない
We’re okay for now if we manage to avoid him.
とにかく今は アイツにさえ
出くわさなければ なんとかなる
What was that?
何？
What’s that?
何だ？
あれ…
Huh?
It moved.
動いた
動いた！
毒じゃないよね？
That’s not poison, right?
違うと思う
I don’t think so.
This is some sort of black powder.
これ 黒い粉だわ
There.
いる あの木の下辺り
Under that tree.
こいつもミュータントだ
It’s another mutant.
What?
そんな！ バケネズミなの？
It’s a queerat?
こいつ 水路を黒く染めて
どうするつもりだ？
What’s the point in fogging up the channel?
No…
違う… 覚！
Satoru!
こいつの目的は水路じゃない
He’s not after the channel.
さっきの爆発 逃げて！
Remember the explosion!
Run!
覚！
Satoru!
I have to survive.
私は生きなければならない
爆発の規模からすれば
Considering the scale of the explosion, the monster had clearly died as well.
あの怪物も死んだのは明白である
It was essentially a suicide attack.
ほとんど自爆に等しい
かつて見た 風船犬は 文字通り
The blowdogs back then sacrificed themselves to try and protect the entrance to the Ground Spider colony,
命を賭して
土蜘蛛の竜穴を守っていたが
粉じんを吐く怪物は 最初から敵
whereas that dust-spewing monster had been bred as a decisive assault weapon against its human enemies.
つまり 人間と刺し違えるために
誕生させられた
攻撃的兵器なのだろう
バケネズミの兵士たちも 全て
All queerat soldiers were no more than pawns in a greater game.
生き物というより
将棋の駒と同じだった
They didn’t mind sacrificing themselves…
犠牲をいとわず というより
Or rather, they launched their attacks intending to die in the process.
はなから捨て駒にするような
攻撃を仕掛けてきている
まさか こんな事態が起こるとは
想像したこともなかった
This was entirely beyond my expectations.
私たちは呪力という
絶対的な強みを信じるあまり
We believed in the absolute power that our Cantus held,
バケネズミを
甘く見すぎていたのかもしれない
and perhaps underestimated the queerats in our vanity.
それにしても 一体 何が
But what drove the queerats to go to such lengths?
バケネズミを
そこまでさせるのだろうか？
あっ あれ？
Huh?
Stop! I’m human!
やめて！ 私 人間よ！
Sorry! I thought you were a queerat!
ごめんなさい バケネズミだと…
Be more careful.
気をつけなきゃ…
私が死んだら
あなたも愧死するのよ
If I’d died, the death feedback would’ve killed you too.
愧死？
Death feedback?
鏑木肆星さんが
守ってくれたんです
Kaburagi Shisei-san protected us.
But many died.
でも たくさん死にました
お父さんとお母さんも
どこにいるのか分からなくて
I don’t know where my parents are either.
ずっと探してるんだけど
I’ve been looking for them all this time.
He was just a child, but he willingly took part in the fighting and witnessed the horror of it.
彼は子供ながら
志願して戦いに参加し
その 一部始終を目撃していた
バケネズミたちが挑んできたのは
徹底したゲリラ戦だった
The queerats were trying to wage an all-out guerrilla war.
それが大きな戦果をあげたのは
Its great success could be attributed to Yakomaru’s tactic of ruthlessly sacrificing his soldiers
野狐丸が兵士を
ただの消耗品としか考えない
非情な戦術を
組み立てたことに加え
人間側に全く戦う準備が
and the complete lack of preparation on part of the humans.
整っていなかったことが
原因だった
非常時に備え
一応の訓練は受けてきたものの
We all had basic training for dealing with emergencies,
いきなり
実戦に放り込まれた人間たちは
but after our home suddenly turned into a battleground,
バケネズミの思うがままに
翻弄され
many of us were helpless before the queerat assault.
犠牲となっていった
思わぬ展開に驚いて
Surprised by the sudden turn of events, groups decided to cooperate,
急きょ
複数の組が連携するようにした
but this, too, proved to be another part of Yakomaru’s strategy.
だが それは ますます野狐丸の
術中に はまる結果となった
It wasn’t just the people mistaken for false humans who died.
ヒトモドキと
間違えられた人だけじゃなくて
The ones who attacked them died, too.
間違えて攻撃した方の人も…
それが愧死よ
That’s death feedback.
未明ごろになると
As dawn drew close, the queerats seemed to have retreated.
バケネズミも ひととおり
一掃されたように見えた
一晩中 続いた
断続的な攻撃も やみ
The attacks that had lasted all night stopped, and so did the influx of casualties.
犠牲者も出なくなった
しかし それは こちらに 一睡も
させないためのものだったようだ
As it turned out, it was merely a ploy to deny us sleep.
多くの人たちが ひと安心して
ウトウトし始めたとき
Many people were relieved and their attention waned.
あの怪物が満を持して登場した
Then those monsters appeared.
深夜のうちに水路を通って
町に侵入し
Under the cover of darkness they entered the town through the canals and waited.
待機していたらしい
それで水路の水を抜いたの？
Is that why you drained the canals?
The town leaders ordered them to be drained.
偉い人たちが
全部 抜くように指示したんです
運河と水路は神栖66町に
網目のように張り巡らされている
A network of waterways and canals
wove through Kamisu’s 66th district.
その全てを監視することが
困難であることを思えば
Guarding them all was unfeasible, so the town took the natural course of action.
当然の策かもしれない
しかし これさえも
計算の上と疑いたくなる
However, one wonders if even this was part of his plans.
大勢の人々が
移動手段を失うことを
Perhaps he did anticipate that many
would lose their only means of transport.
見越していたのかもしれない
他に何か もっと恐ろしいこと
聞かなかった？
Did you hear about anything worse than that?
もっと って？
Worse than that?
ううん 変なこと聞いてごめんね
Never mind. Sorry about the weird question.
人間たちは 終始
Yakomaru had us humans in the palm of his hand from beginning to end.
野狐丸の手のひらで
踊らされていた
お願い 水を…
Please… Water… I need water…
水をちょうだい
今 くんできます
ちょっと待ってて下さい！
I’ll bring you some!
Please wait!
僕がやるから行って
うん…
I’ll take care of this. Go.
Okay.
偉い人のところに行かなきゃ
ならないって言ってたじゃない
You said you really have to talk to the town leaders, right?
早く行って！
Hurry!
待って
Wait.
ごめんなさい
私 富子様か肆星さんに
I’m sorry.
I really need to talk to Tomiko-sama or Shisei-san!
伝えなきゃならないことが
あるんです
富子様なら…
Tomiko-sama will be…
富子様なら全人学級よ
Tomiko-sama will be at Sage Academy.
あそこは まだ建物が無事だから
It should still be standing.
あ… ありがとうございます
Thank you.
こちらです
This way.
早季ちゃん
はい
Saki-chan…
Yes.
よかったわ あなたが無事で
I’m so glad you’re okay.
おケガをなさったんですね
You’re wounded…
ううん 大したことはないの
It isn’t serious.
それより 私に伝えたいことって
いうのは 何？
But what did you want to tell me?
はい
Very well.
ありえないわ
いくら早季ちゃんの言葉でも
Impossible.
I trust you greatly, but I will not believe it.
信じられない
I know what I saw.
ウソじゃありません！
現に 私の目の前で
Two people were killed right in front of my eyes.
２人 殺されたんです
だけど 理屈に合わないわ
どうして 今なの？
But it doesn’t make sense.
Why now?
教育委員会が
あれほど厳重に管理していたのに
The Board of Education was so careful.
分かりません でも 一体 誰が
I don’t know.
But what else could use Cantus to kill people?
人間を呪力で
殺害できるっていうんですか？
I beg you!
お願いです！ このままだと
Things might go out of control if we don’t act.
本当に取り返しのつかないことに
なります
今すぐ 何らかの手を打たないと！
We have to do something and—
打つ手は ないのよ
There is nothing we can do.
２世紀以上前 この町は
あの惨劇から見事に復活しました
But two centuries ago the town
managed to recover from that tragedy!
それを目撃されたのは
あなたご自身じゃないですか！
Didn’t you live to see it?
あのときは
とてつもなく幸運だったのよ
We were extraordinarily lucky then.
But…
そんな…
新見さん 何の騒ぎなの
Why the commotion, Niimi-san?
悪鬼だそうです
A fiend has been sighted.
A fiend?!
私は ここに とどまるわ
I will stay here.
足手まといにしかならないから
I would only slow you down.
でも…
But…
清浄寺へ行きなさい
Go to the Temple of Purity.
安全保障委員会では
The Security Council should be recuperating there.
あそこで態勢を立て直す
手はずになっています
Your parents should be there as well, if they survived.
あなたのご両親も
無事なら避難しているはずです
ずっと以前に
私が言ったことを覚えてますか？
Do you remember what I said a long time ago?
Huh?
I was serious.
あれは私の本心でした
こんな形で引き継がなければ
ならないのは残念ですが
I’m sorry you have to succeed me in such a fashion,
神栖66町をあなたに託します
but I’m leaving Kamisu’s 66th district in your care.
待ってください
私 そんな とても…
Wait a moment.
I can’t…
That’s…
新見さん あなたも早季ちゃんと
逃げてください
Niimi-san, please make your escape together with Saki-chan.
富子様がお逃げにならんのなら
私も ここに おります
If you will not escape, then neither will I.
いいえ
あなたには 別の使命を与えます
No, I’m giving you another task to do.
But…
私は…
肆星に 今の話を伝えて下さい
Tell Shisei what you heard here.
そして 公民館に行って
放送をして下さい
Then go to the town hall and give a broadcast.
できるだけ多くの人たちに
なるべく遠くへ逃げるよう
Tell as many townspeople as possible that they are to run as far as they can.
警告を発するのです
分かりました
As you wish.
さあ 何をしているの？
早く行きなさい！
What are you still doing here?
Go!
でも…
But—
待って！
富子様が このままじゃ…
Wait!
Tomiko-sama will—
This is her wish.
これが富子様のご意思なのです
Nani mo iranai
何もいらない
I need nothing else
Anata ga ireba ii
あなたがいればいい
When you are by my side
Sotto yokogao iki wo korosu
そっと横顔 息を殺す
I look at you in profile and hold my breath
Mabataki sureba kieteshimaisou de
まばたきすれば消えてしまいそうで
I'm afraid it might vanish like an illusion if I blink now
Mitsumesasete suki da yo
凝視めさせて好きだよ
Let me look at you, I love you
Ah kigi ga furue furidashita yuki
ああ 木々が震え 降り出した雪
The trees shake in the wind and snow gathers on the ground
Ashiato futatsu shiroku
足跡 ふたつ 白く
Two lines of white footprints show
Toki yo tsumore
時よ 積もれ
Snowflakes of time, gather
Kami ni mune ni futari dake no yume ni
髪に 胸に ふたりだけの夢に
In our hair, our hearts, our dream
Sakenai hana no
咲けない花の
This flower cannot bloom
Tane wa yuki ni dakare
種は雪に抱かれ
And the snow embraces its seeds
Yorisou no
寄り添うの
As they huddle together
Shizuka ni wasureraretai
静かに忘れられたい
Quietly they wish to be able to forget
FROM
THE
NEW
WORLD
Let us vow to eradicate the queerat race from the land of the gods, from the archipelago of Japan!
バケネズミという種そのものを
神の国 日本列島から根絶やしに
することを約束しよう
ヤ ヤメロ…
S-Stop!
呪力の漏出…
Cantus leakage?
うわぁ～！